Nine years ago, I worked
قبل تسع سنوات، عملت
for the U.S. government in Iraq,
للحكومة الأمريكية في العراق
helping rebuild the electricity infrastructure.
للمساعدة في إعادة تركيب البنية التحتية للكهرباء
And I was there, and I worked in that job
لقد كنت هناك، وعملت في تلك الوظيفة
because I believe that technology
لأنني أؤمن بأن التقنية
can improve people's lives.
بإمكانها تطوير حياة البشر
One afternoon, I had tea with a storekeeper
ذات مساء، شربت الشاي مع أحد حراس المستودع
at the Al Rasheed Hotel in Baghdad,
في فندق الرشيد في بغداد
and he said to me, "You Americans,
وقال لي: "أنتم الأمريكان
you can put a man on the moon,
تستطيعون أن تضعوا رجلا فوق سطح القمر،
but when I get home tonight,
ولكن عندما أرجع للبيت
I won't be able to turn on my lights."
لن أستطيع أن أغلق الأنوار"
At the time, the U.S. government had spent
في ذلك الوقت، الحكومة الأمريكية كانت قد أنفقت
more than two billion dollars
أكثر من ملياري دولار
on electricity reconstruction.
على إعادة بناء الكهرباء.
How do you ensure technology reaches users?
كيف يمكنك التأكد من وصول التقنية للمستخدمين؟
How do you put it in their hands
كيف تضعها في أيديهم
so that it is useful?
بحيث تكون ذات فائدة؟
So those are the questions that my colleagues and I
هذا نوع الأسئلة التي نطرحها أنا وزملائي
at D-Rev ask ourselves.
في دي ريف على أنفسنا
And D-Rev is short for Design Revolution.
ودي ريف هي اختصار لثورة التصميم
And I took over the organization four years ago
وقد أخذت بزمام الأمور في المنظمة قبل أربع سنوات
and really focused it on developing products
وكان تركيزي منصبا على تطوير المنتجات
that actually reach users,
التي تصل للمستخدمين فعليا،
and not just any users,
ليس أي مستخدم،
but customers who live on less than four dollars a day.
ولكن المستخدمين الذين يتقاضون أقل من أربع دولاارات يوميا
One of the key areas we've been working on recently
أحد االمشاريع المهمة التي نعمل عليها حديثا
is medical devices, and while it may not be obvious
هو أجهزة طبية, وقد لا يكون واضحا
that medical devices have something in common
أن تلك الأجهزة الطبية لديها شيء مشترك
with Iraq's electricity grid then,
مع شبكة الكهرباء في العراق
there are some commonalities.
هنالك بعض القواسم المشتركة
Despite the advanced technology,
بغض النظرعن التقنية المتقدمة
it's not reaching the people who need it most.
إنها لا تصل إلى الناس الذين يحتاجونها أكثر من غيرهم.
So I'm going to tell you about one of the projects we've been working on,
لذا سأخبركم عن أحد المشاريع التي نعمل عليها
the ReMotion Knee, and it's a prosthetic knee
ركبة إعادة الحركة، وهي ركبة اصطناعية
for above-knee amputees.
مصممة لمبتوري الأطراف
And this project started when the Jaipur Foot Organization,
وهذا المشروع ابتدأ عندما أتت منظمة جايبور فووت،
the largest fitter of prosthetic limbs in the world,
وهي أكبر منظمة متخصصة بالأطراف الصناعية في العالم،
came to the Bay Area and they said,
أتت إلى منطقة الخليج وقالوا:
"We need a better knee."
" نحتاج إلى ركبة أفضل"
Chances are, if you're living on less than four dollars a day,
الفرص هنا, إذا كنت تتقاضى أقل من أربع دولارات باليوم،
and you're an amputee,
ولديك طرف مبتور
you've lost your limb in a vehicle accident.
حيث فقدت أحد أطرافك في حادث سيارة.
Most people think it's land mines,
أغلب الناس يطنون أنها بسبب الألغام
but it's a vehicle accident.
ولكنه حادث سيارة
You're walking by the side of the road
تمشي على جانب الطريق
and you're hit by a truck,
ثم تصطدم بك شاحنة
or you're trying to to jump on a moving train,
أو أن تقفز من أمام قطار
you're late for work, and your pant leg gets caught.
عندما تكون متأخرا عن العمل، وتتعثر بطرف بنطالك
And the reality is that if you don't have much money,
وإذا كنت في الواقع لا تملك القدر الكلفي من المال
like this young named Kamal right here,
مثل هذا الشاب كامال الجالس هنا
the option you really have
الاختيار الذي تملكه في الواقع
is a bamboo staff to get around.
هو عصا الخيزران لتقوم باللالتفاف.
And how big a problem is this?
ما هو حجم هذه المشكلة إذا؟
There's over three million amputees every year
هنالك أكثر من ثلاث ملايين مبتورين أطراف كل سنة
who need a new or replacement knee.
وهم يحتاجون لاستبدال ركبهم المصابة بركبة جديدة
And what are their options?
ماهي خياراتهم؟
This is a high-end. This is what we'd call a "smart knee."
هذه هي النهاية الراقية. هذا ما نسميه بالركبة الذكية
It's got a microprocessor inside.
والتي تحتوي على مشغلات دقيقة في الداخل
It can pretty much do anything,
وتستطيع إلى حد كبير أن تقوم بعمل أي شي
but it's 20,000 dollars,
ولكن قيمتها عشرين ألف دولار
and to give you a sense of who wears this,
ولكي تستطيون أن تفهموا من يستطيع إقتناء هذا النوع،
veterans, American veterans coming back from Afghanistan or Iraq
المحاربين القدامى، قدامى المحاربين الامريكان الذين رجعوا من أفغانستان أو العراق
would be fit with something like this.
سيكونون مناسبين لهذا النوع
This is a low-end titanium knee.
هذا جزء سفلي من ركبة صناعية مصنوعة من التاتينيوم
It's a polycentric knee, and all that that means
وهي ركبة صناعية متعددة المراكز، وكل هذا يعني
is the mechanism, is a four-bar mechanism,
أن طريقة عملها يكون بواسطة أربع قضبان
that mimics a natural human knee.
بشكل يحاكي الركبة البشرية الطبيعية
But at 1,400 dollars, it's still too expensive
ولكن بقيمة 1400 دولار، القيمة لازالت مرتفعة
for people like Kamal.
على أشخاص مثل كمال
And lastly, here you see a low-end knee.
أخيرا، تشاهدون هنا الطرف السفلي من الركبة
This is a knee that's been designed specifically
وهي مصممة خصيصا
for poor people.
للفقراء
And while you have affordability,
وعندما تكون لديك القدرة المالية
you've lost on functionality.
تكون خسرت على الأداء
The mechanism here is a single axis,
طريقة العمل هنا تكون بواسطة محور واحد
and a single axis is like a door hinge.
والمحور الواحد يكون مثل مفصل الباب
So you can think about how unstable that would be.
ولكم أن تتخيلوا كيف أن هذا الشيء سيكون غير مستقر
And this is the type of mechanism
وهذا النوع من طريقة العمل
that the Jaipur Foot Organization was using when they were looking for a better knee,
الذي كانت تستخدمه منظمة جوبير فوت عندما كانوا يبحثون عن ركبة أفضل
and I just wanted to give you a sense of what a leg system looks like,
أردت فقط أن أعطيكم معنى بسيط لطريقة عمل نظام دعم الأطراف الاصطناعية
because I'm showing you all these knees
لأنني أعرض لكم كل هذه الأنواع من الركب الاصطناعية
and I imagine it's hard to think how it all fits together.
وأعرف أنه من الصعب تخيل كل هذه الأطراف مجتمعة مع بعضها
So at the top you have a socket,
لذا، تشاهدون هذا التجويف في الأعلى
and this fits over someone's residual limb,
وهذا يناسب تجويف فخذ أحدهم
and everyone's residual limb is a little bit different.
وكل تجويف فخذي يختلف من شخص لآخر
And then you have the knee,
وبعدها تشاهد الركبة
and here I've got a single axis on the knee
حيف تشاهدون المحور الواحد على الركبة
so you can see how it rotates,
لتتمكنوا من مشاهدة طريقة دورانها
and then a pylon, and then a foot.
ثم هنا الساق الاصطناعية، وبعدها القدم
And we've been able to develop a knee,
وقد استطعنا تطوير ركبة اصطناعية
a polycentric knee, so that type of knee
وهي ركبة متعددة المراكز، حيث أن مثل هذا النوع
that acts like a human knee, mimics human gait,
يعمل مثل الركبة البشرية الطبيعية، ويحاكي طريقة مشيهم
for 80 dollars retail.
بقيمة 80 دولار
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But the key is, you can have this great invention,
ولكن السر هنا أنكم تستطيعون امتلاك هذا الاختراع العظيم
you can have this great design, but how do you get it
مع هذا التصميم الرائع، ولكن كيف تتمكنون من الحصول عليها
to the people who most need it?
لإعطائها للأشخاص الذين يحتاجونها بشدة؟
How do you ensure it gets to them and it improves their lives?
كيف تتأكدون أنها تصل إليهم وتساعدهم على تطوير حياتهم؟
So at D-Rev, we've done some other projects,
لذا في دي ريف، قمنا بعمل بعض المشاريع الأخرى
and we looked at three things that we really believe
وكان تركيزنا منصبا على 3 أشياء رئيسية نؤمن بها جميعا
gets technologies to customers, to users,
إيصال التقنية للزبائن, وللمستخدمين،
to people who need it.
لمن يحتاجها من الناس
And the first thing is that the product needs to be world class.
و أول شيء هو أن هذا المنتج يجب أن يكون عالميا
It needs to perform on par
لابد أن يعمل بنفس المستوى
or better than the best products on the market.
أو أفضل من المنتجات الموجودة بالسوق
Regardless of your income level,
بغض النظر عن مستوى دخلك
you want the most beautiful,
تريد أجمل الأشياء
the best product that there is.
أفضل المنتجات الموجودة
I'm going to show you a video now
سأعرض لكم مقطع فديو الآن
of a man named Ash. You can see him walking.
عن رجل اسمه آش، يمكنكم مشاهدته يمشي
He's wearing the same knee system here
وهو يستخدم مثل الركبة الاصطناعية الموجودة هنا
with a single axis knee.
مع محور واحد على الركبة
And he's doing a 10-meter walk test.
وهو يؤدي اختبار المشي لمسافة 10 أمتار
And you'll notice that he's struggling with stability as he's walking.
وستلاحظون أنه يقاوم من أجل الحصول على التوازن أثناء المشي
And something that's not obvious, that you can't see,
وشيء آخر غير واضح ولا يمكنكم مشاهدته
is that it's psychologically draining
وهو أنه يستنزف من الناحية النفسية
to walk and to be preventing yourself from falling.
أن تمشي وتحاول أن تمنع نفسك من السقوط
Now this is a video of Kamal.
الآن تشاهدون هذا الفديو لكمال
You remember Kamal earlier, holding the bamboo staff.
تتذكرون كمال في البداية عندما كان ممسكا بعصا من الخيزران
He's wearing one of the earlier versions of our knee,
هنا يرتدي أواحدة من أول منتجاتنا من الركب الاصطناعية
and he's doing that same 10-meter walk test.
ويقوم بأداء اختبار المشي لمسافة 10 أمتار
And you can see his stability is much better.
يمكنكم المشاهدة هنا أن التوازن أفضل بكثير
So world class isn't just about technical performance.
لذلك أن تكون عالميا لا يعني فقط من الناحية التقنية
It's also about human performance.
ولكن أيضا يعني الأداء البشري
And most medical devices, we've learned,
وقد تعلمنا أن أغلب الأجهزة الطبية
as we've dug in, are really designed for Westerners,
كما أوضحنا، مصممات خصيصا للغربيين
for wealthier economies.
لأجل اقتصاد أقوى
But the reality is our users, our customers,
لكن في الحقيقة أن مستخدمينا، وزبائننا
they do different things. They sit cross-legged more.
يعملون أشياء مختلفة. يضعون أرجلهم فوق بعضها
We see that they squat. They kneel in prayer.
يجلسون، يركعون في الصلاة
And we designed our knee to have the greatest range of motion
وقد صممنا هذه الركبة لإعطاء أعلى مجال ممكن للحركة
of almost any other knee on the market.
أفضل من أغلب الركب الاصطناعية الموجودة في السوق
So the second thing we learned, and this leads
لذا، الشيء الثاني الذي تعلمناه، وهذا الشيء يقود
into my second point, which is that we believe
لنقطة أخرى، وهي أننا نؤمن
that products need to be designed to be user-centric.
أن المنتجات لابد أن تكون مصممة لتتمحور حول المستخدم
And at D-Rev, we go one step further and we say
و في دي ريف، نتقدم بخطوة إلى الأمام ونقول
you need to be user-obsessed.
لابد أن تكون مهووس بالمستخدم
So it's not just the end user that you're thinking about,
لذا أنت لا تفكر بالمستخدم الأخير فقط
but everyone who interacts with the product,
ولكنك تفكر بكل شخص يتعامل مع المنتج
so, for example, the prosthetist who fits the knee,
مثلا: الشخص المتخصص بتركيب الأطراف الاصطناعية
but also the context in which the knee is being fit.
ولكن السياق أيضا وكيف يمكن أن تتناسب الركبة الاصطناعية معه
What is the local market like?
ما هو شكل السوق المحلية؟
How do all these components get to the clinic?
كيف يتم نقل كل هذه المكونات إلى العيادة؟
Do they all get there on time? The supply chain.
هل تصل جميع هذه الأجزاء في الوقت المناسب؟
Everything that goes into ensuring
وكل شيء يساعد على تأكيد
that this product gets to the end user,
أن هذا المنتج يصل للمستخدم النهائي
and it goes in as part of the system, and it's used.
ويتم استدعائها كجزء من النظام واستخداماته
So I wanted to show you some of the iterations
لذ أريد أن أعرض لكم بعض االتطورات
we did between the first version, the Jaipur Knee,
التي عملناها بين أول نسخة والمسماة بركبة جيبور
so this is it right here.
وهي كما تشاهدون هنا
(Clicking)
(قرقعة)
Notice anything about it?
هل تلاحظون أي شيء حولها؟
It clicks.
إنها تقرقع
We'd seen that users had actually modified it.
لاحظنا أن المستخدمين في الواقع عدلوا عليها
So do you see that black strip right there?
هل تلاحظون الشريط الأسود هنالك؟
That's a homemade noise dampener.
هذا مانع للصوت مصنوع بالبيت
We also saw that our users had modified it
وأيضا لاحظنا أن مستخدمينا قد عدلوا عليها
in other ways.
بطرق أخرى
You can see there that that particular amputee,
يمكنكم أن تشاهدوا هنا هذا الشخص المبتور
he had wrapped bandages around the knee.
قام بلف ضمادات حول الركبة
He'd made a cosmesis.
وقد عدل على الشكل الخارجي
And if you look at the knee,
وإذا نظرتوا إلى الركبة
it's got those pointy edges, right?
تشاهدون هذه الأطراف المدببة، هل هذا صحيح؟
So if you're wearing it under pants or a skirt
لذا إذا كنتم مرتدينها تحت البنطال أو التنورة
or a sari, it's really obvious
أو الساري، فهذا سيكون واضح جدا
that you're wearing a prosthetic limb,
أنك ترتدي طرفا صناعيا
and in societies where there's social stigma around being disabled,
وفي المجتمعات التي يكون فيها عيوب اجتماعية حول الاعاقة
people are particularly acute about this.
الناس يكونون متحفظين على هذا الموضوع
So I'm going to show you some of the modifications we did.
لذا سأعرض لكم بعض التعديلات التي عملنا
We did a lot of iterations, not just around this, but some other things.
قمنا بتطوير الكثير من الأشياء، ليس لهذا الشيء فقط ولكن لأشياء أخرى
But here we have the version three, the ReMotion Knee,
هنا تشاهدون النسخة الثالثة، ركبة إعادة الحركة الاصطناعية
but if you look in here, you can see
ولكن إذا أمعنتوا النظر هنا، يمكنكم مشاهدة
the noise dampener. It's quieter.
كاتم الصوت، إنها أقل إزعاجا
The other thing we did is that we smoothed the profile.
الشيء الآخر الذي قمنا بعمله هو أننا صقلنا الوجه
We made it thinner.
قمنا بجعلها أنحف
And something that's not obvious is that we
وشيء آخر لا يمكن ملاحظته من الخارج وهو أننا
designed it for mass production.
صممناها لإنتاج كميات ضخمة
And this goes into my last point.
وهذا يأخذني للنقطة الأخيرة
We really, truly believe that if a product
في الحقيقة والواقع، إذا كان هنالك منتج
is going to reach users at the scale that it's needed,
وهذا المنتج سيصل للمستخدمين ويكون على مستوى توقعاتهم
it needs to be market-driven,
لابد أن يكون هذا المنتج مطلوب بالسوق
and market-driven means that products are sold.
ومعنى أن يكون مطلوبا بالسوق هو أن المنتجات يتم بيعها
They're not donated. They're not heavily subsidized.
وليس التبرع بها أو دعمها
Our product needs to be designed to offer value
منتجاتنا يجب تصميمها لتقدم قيمة
to the end user.
للمستخدم الأخير للمنتج
It also has to be designed to be very affordable.
يجب أيضا أن تكون مصممة بحيث أن تكون سهلة المنال
But a product that is valued by a customer
ولكن المنتج المعتبر بعين الزبون
is used by a customer,
هو المستخدم من قبل هذا الزبون
and use is what creates impact.
والاستخدام هو الذي يخلق التأثير
And we believe that as designers,
ونحن بصفتنا مصممين، نؤمن بأن
it holds us accountable to our customers.
هذا ما يجعلنا محاسبين أمام زبائننا
And with centralized manufacturing,
ومع مركزية التصنيع
you can control the quality control,
يمكن السيطرة على جودة التحكم
and you can hit that $80 price point
ويمكنك الوصول لقيمة 80 دولار
with profit margins built in.
مع تراكم هوامش الأرباح
And now, those profit margins are critical,
و الأرباح مهمة جدا
because if you want to scale, if you want to reach
لأنك إذا أردت أن تتوازن، وأن تصل
all the people in the world who possibly need a knee,
إلى جميع الأشخاص الموجودين في العالم والذين يحتاجون إلى ركبة اصطناعية
it needs to be economically sustainable.
يجب أن تكون متوازن من الناحية الاقتصادية
So I want to give you a sense of where we are at.
لذا أردت أن أعرض لكم إلى أي مدى وصلنا
We have fit over 5,000 amputees,
استطعنا خدمة أكثر من 5000 من مبتوري الأطراف
and one of the big indicators we're looking at, of course,
وأحد أهم المؤشرات التي نبحث عنها بالطبع
is, does it improve lives?
هي، هل هي تساعد فعلا على تطوير نسق الحياة؟
Well, the standard is, is someone
حسنا، المقياس هو، هل هنالك شخص
still wearing their knee six months later?
لازال يلبس الركبة الاصطناعية بعد 6 أشهر؟
The industry average is about 65 percent.
معدل الصناعة هو 65 بالمئة
Ours is 79 percent,
ومعدلنا الخاص هو 79 بالمئة
and we're hoping to get that higher.
ونحن نطمح بأن نكون الأعلى.
Right now, our knees are worn in 12 countries.
حاليا، الركب الاصطناعية خاصتنا مستخدمة في 12 دولة
This is where we want to get, though,
هنا ما نريد الوصول إليه، بالرغم أننا
in the next three years.
وفي الثلاث سنوات القادمة،
We'll double the impact in 2015,
سوف نضاعف التأثير في 2015
and we'll double it each of the following years after that.
وسوف نضاعفها في كل سنة بعد ذلك.
But then we hit a new challenge,
ولكننا اصطدمنا بتحدي جديد
and that's the number of skilled prosthetists
وهو عدد أصحاب المهارة المتخصصين بتركيب الأطراف الاصطناعية
who are able to fit knees.
والذين يستطيعون تركيب هذا النوع من الركب
So I want to end with a story of Pournima.
لذا أريد أن أنهي بقصة لبرانيما
Pournima was 18 years old
برانيما كان عمرها 18 سنة
when she was in a car accident where she lost her leg,
عندما تعرضت لحادث سيارة حيث فقدت ساقها
and she traveled 12 hours by train
وقد سافرت لمدة 12 ساعة بالقطار
to come to the clinic to be fit with a knee,
للقدوم إلى العيادة الطبية ليتم تركيب ركبة اصطناعية لها
and while all of the amputees who wear our knees
وعندما كان جميع مبتوري الأطراف من مستخدمي الركبة الاصطناعية التي أنتجناها
affect us as the designers,
يؤثرون علينا كمصممين
she's particularly meaningful to me as an engineer and as a woman,
هي لها معنى خاص عندي كمهندسة وامرأة أيضا
because she was in school,
لأنها كانت تدرس في المدرسة
she had just started school to study engineering.
ولقد بدأت للتو دراستها للهندسة
And she said, "Well, now that I can walk again,
وقد قالت: "حسنا، الآن أستطيع المشي مجددا،
I can go back and complete my studies."
أنا أستطيع الرجوع واكمال دراستي"
And to me she represents the next generation
وبالنسبة لي، هي تمثل الجيل القدام
of engineers solving problems
للمهندسين الذين يحلون المعضلات
and ensuring meaningful technologies
ويتأكدون من أن التقنية بمعناها العميق
reach their users.
تصل لمستخدميهم
So thank you.
حسنا، شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)